Shri Mataji: Have the Americans come, those who have done the Puja, have they come?
آمریکایی‌ها آمده‌اند؟ آنها که پوجا کرد‌ه‌اند، آیا آمده‌اند؟
Sahaja yogi: Yes, Mother. Shri Mataji: Are they here? Man: Yes.
ساهاجایوگی: بله مادر. اینجا هستند؟ ساهاجایوگی: بله
Shri Mataji: Oh, they are here. Then it’s all right.
آنها اینجا هستند، پس خوب است
And, in these new centers,
و در این مراکز جدید،
have you started with Puja anywhere? Sahaja Yogini: Yes, Mother.
آیا با پوجا جایی را افتتاح کرده‌اید؟ ساهاجایوگینی: بله مادر
Shri Mataji: No, yours is all right, I’m asking about England.
نه، مرکز شما خوب است، درباره انگلستان می‌پرسم.
Warren: Any centres in Britain? Where there are new people.
وارن: از تمام مراکز انگلیس؟ آیا فرد جدیدی اینجا هست؟
Shri Mataji: Cheltenham, for example. Where is Alan? Ask him.
چلتنهام مثلا؛ آلن کجاست؟ از او بپرسید.
Warren: He’s just gone out for a moment. Any centers in Britain,
وارن: همین الان یک دقیقه بیرون رفت از تمام مراکز انگلیس،
any new people here, right now?
آیا فرد جدیدی اینجا هست، همین الان؟
Shri Mataji: If do you have introduced them to puja I don’t mind,
اگر پوجا را برایشان توضیح داده‌اید، مهم نیست
but if they have never been introduced to puja, then you have to be careful.
ولی اگر هیچ‌وقت پوجا را برایشان توضیح نداده‌اید، پس باید مراقب باشید؛
From their good point of view.
به خاطر مصلحت خودشان.
I’m sorry I had to say this,
متأسفم که مجبور شدم این را بگویم،
because yesterday the load was too much, you know I couldn’t speak even,
دیروز جمعیت خیلی زیاد بود، طوری که حتی نمی‌توانستم صحبت کنم
and lifting the Kundalini was like raising hundred donkeys on your head,
و بالا آوردن کندالینی مثل این بود که بخواهی صد تا الاغ را روی سرت بلند کنی،
it was too much.
خیلی سخت بود
And all these half-baked people are such that they are like dog-in-the-manger,
و همه این افراد خام، نه خود استفاده می‌کنند و نه اجازه استفاده به دیگران می‌دهند،
they won’t have it and they won’t allow others to have it.
آنها بهره‌ای نمی‌برند و نمی‌گذارند بقیه هم بهره‌مند شوند
They’ll argue before the program, before the meeting starts,
آنها قبل از برنامه، قبل از شروع جلسه،
before the puja starts, specially.
مخصوصا قبل از شروع پوجا جر و بحث می‌کنند
Because they don’t want you to enjoy the fruits of the puja;
چون نمی‌خواهند از ثمره پوجا لذت ببرید.
they’ll spoil your attention,
آنها توجه شما را خراب می‌کنند،
they’ll argue, discuss. [Aside: “Please sit down.”]
آنها جدل می‌کنند، جر و بحث می‌کنند؛ لطفا بنشینید.
What is there to argue in Sahaj Yoga? You have to take, that’s the point is,
ساهاجایوگا چه چیزی برای بحث دارد؟ شما باید جذب کنید، نکته این است که
you have to take, there’s nothing to argue.
شما باید جذب کنید. چیزی برای جر و بحث وجود ندارد.
How much you take is the point.
نکته این است که چقدر جذب می‌کنید؛
And the worst part is that they don’t want to grow and they want to pull you down.
و بدتر از همه این‌ که آنها نمی‌خواهند رشد کنند و می‌خواهند شما را هم پایین بکشند.
So, unless and until they are introduced to the idea of puja beforehand -
پس، وقتی قبل از پوجا معنی آن توضیح داده شود
then they start understanding the worth of puja, otherwise they do not,
به ارزش پوجا پی خواهند برد، در غیر این صورت نمی‌فهمند؛
how will they understand? You see, it’s beyond them.
چطور بفهمند؟ می‌دانید، این برایشان زیاد است.
So, you should not make them attend any puja, minimum,
پس شما اصلا وادارشان نکنید در هیچ پوجایی شرکت کنند، حداقل
and also seminars I would say. Because seminars are meant for people
و باید بگویم، در سمینارها هم همین‌طور؛ چون سمینارها به درد کسانی می‌خورد
who are intensively in Sahaj Yoga, to intensify their awareness.
که در مورد ساهاجایوگا جدی هستند، تا آگاهی‌شان را تقویت کنند
Not for people who are half-baked, who are Doubting Thomases,
نه برای افراد خامی که به هر چیزی شک دارند،
all this kind of people are absolutely useless,
هیچ کدام از این افراد اصلا به درد نمی‌خورند،
you should never bring them to a seminar.
و شما نباید هرگز آنها را به سمینار بیاورید.
Whether it’s your son, father, brother, mother, sister, husband, wife,
چه پسر، پدر، برادر، مادر، خواهر، شوهر یا زنتان باشند،
nothing doing. You shouldn’t bring anybody who is not
به هیچ وجه. شما نباید ساهاجایوگی‌ای که کاملا آگاه نیست بیاورید.
because seminars are meant for very intensive work-out.
چون سمینارها به درد کار فشرده می‌خورد
And what I find, always these people will argue with Me,
و می‌بینم، همیشه این افراد با من بحث می‌کنند
they are the first to question, they have something to say
اولین کسی که سوال می‌پرسد این‌ها هستند، یک چیزی دارند بگویند،
they are the ones. Sahaja Yogis are keeping quiet and receiving it.
همین‌ها هستند. ساهاجایوگی‌ها ساکت می‌نشینند و آن را جذب می‌کنند.
I don’t mind even that, but what happens in the seminar, you have to receive more.
حتی این هم برای من مهم نیست. اما آن‌چه در سمینارها جریان دارد، باید بیشتر جذب کنید
And they do not receive, their attention is outside, they are disturbing everyone.
و آنها جذب نمی‌کنند، توجهشان به ظاهر است. آنها مزاحم همه می‌شوند.
So, seminars are even, in a way, more important than an ashram,
پس، سمینارها، حتی به شکلی مهم‌تر از اشرام هستند
because in ashram there’s no other problem but to fight them out.
چون در اشرام هیچ مشکلی جز متقاعد کردن آنها وجود ندارد.
But here, in a new place we go, we have to fight out all surroundings,
اما اینجا، هر جای جدیدی که می‌رویم باید تمام اطرافیان را متقاعد کنیم.
the place itself has to be cleansed, everything has to be done.
خود محل هم باید تمیز شود، هر کاری باید انجام شود.
On top of that you have these horrible people around you,
از همه بدتر، این افراد مزخرف دور و بر شما هستند
whom you have to convince. If they are not convinced, why are they here?
که باید قانعشان کنید اگر قانع نشده‌اند، اینجا چه می‌کنند؟
Why did they spend so much money to come down?
چرا این همه پول خرج کرده‌اند اینجا بیایند؟
Be sure, they have come here to disturb us. I’m sorry we had to do that way.
شک نکنید اینجا آمده‌اند تا مزاحم ما شوند متأسفم، مجبور بودیم این‌طور عمل کنیم
I wish people could be simple, straightforward,
ای کاش می‌شد مردم ساده، روراست،
uncomplicated, and sensitive, but they are not.
بی‌غل و غش و ظریف باشند؛ اما نیستند.
They are not sensitive people. They don’t understand what are they up to.
آنها آدم‌های ظریفی نیستند. نمی‌دانند قرار است چه کنند.
By that they destroy themselves, no doubt, but they destroy part of you also,
با این کار آنها خودشان را نابود می‌کنند، شکی نیست؛ اما آنها تعدادی از شماها را هم نابود می‌کنند
and also trouble Me. Yesterday it was too heavy, you know that.
و مرا نیز به دردسر می‌اندازند دیروز برنامه خیلی سنگین بود، این را می‌دانید
Such a deep subject and it was too heavy for Me.
چنین موضوع عمیقی؛ و این برای من خیلی سنگین بود
If they say they feel bad, all right, tell them: “We are sorry, we can’t help you.”
اگر می‌گویند حس بدی دارند، بسیار خوب، به آنها بگویید: ببخشید، کاری از دست ما برنمی‌آید.
See, there are certain points where we have to have our freedom
می‌دانید، جاهای خاصی هستند که ما باید اختیار ورود افراد را داشته باشیم. آنجاست که ما، در را می‌بندیم
And there’s nothing wrong in it, because you have to equip more to pull them out.
و هیچ اشکالی هم در این کار نیست؛ چون شما باید خوب آماده شوید تا آنها را نجات دهید.
It has been always our practice, since long, there’s nothing new about it,
کار ما از قدیم، همیشه همین بوده است، چیز تازه‌ای نیست؛
everyone knows, not only in England, or any other place, even in India:
همه می‌دانند، نه تنها در انگلیس یا هرجای دیگری، حتی در هند.
we never allowed anybody to come for the Puja who was not a realized soul,
ما هیچ‌وقت به کسی که خودآگاه یا ساهاجایوگی نبوده، اجازه ورود به پوجا ندادیم؛ از همان ابتدا.
Wherever we tried that, we found it was very difficult.
هر جا این را امتحان کردیم، فهمیدیم خیلی سخت است
So I hope there’s nobody sitting here with a doubting mind.
پس امیدوارم اینجا هیچ‌کس با ذهنی شکاک ننشسته باشد
If somebody’s there he should with all sincerity leave the hall
اگر کسی هست، خودش باید صادقانه سالن را ترک کند
and leave us alone, for the ascent.
و دست از سر ما بردارد تا تعالی یابیم.
Anybody who has doubts should be kind and generous about it.
هر کس شک دارد، باید با لطف و بزرگواری برخورد کند.
It’s a very serious work we are doing. It’s not of making money
کاری که داریم انجام می‌دهیم بسیار جدی است. موضوع پول درآوردن
or of throwing an enterprise or building a house or something like that.
یا راه انداختن کار و کاسبی یا ساخت و ساز یک خانه یا چیزی مثل آن نیست
It’s not even just making creations of worlds,
حتی صرفا خلق جهان هم نیست،
it’s much more than that, it’s a very serious work we are doing
خیلی بالاتر از آن است؛ کاری بسیار جدی است که داریم انجام می‌دهیم.
and we don’t want anybody to cut our attention.
نمی‌خواهیم کسی توجه ما را منحرف کند؛
Even some of the Sahaja Yogis I know, are half-baked.
حتی بعضی از ساهاجایوگی‌ها را می‌شناسم که خام هستند
They must be corrected, all right, doesn’t matter, but they have been exposed to pujas,
آنها باید اصلاح شوند، بسیار خوب، ایرادی ندارد، ولی در پوجاها بوده‌اند.
so it will do them good, not bad.
پس این برایشان خوب است، بد نیست.
But some people are just anti-God, and they have allergies for God.
ولی بعضی از افراد واقعا ضد خدا هستند و به خداوند حساسیت دارند.
Any work you’d start doing in the name of God, they are so allergic, they react.
هرکاری را بخواهید به اسم خداوند شروع کنید، بسیار حساس می‌شوند و واکنش نشان می‌دهند.
These are anti-God allergies,
اینها حساسیت‌های ضد خدایی هستند
and they express themselves by different, funny methods.
که به شکل‌های مسخره‌ای خود را نشان می‌دهند.
Now, all the Sahaja Yogis must know this, then you will not go too far with them.
حال، همه ساهاجایوگی‌ها باید این را بدانند، آن وقت حد را برای آنها نگه ‌می‌دارید
You will - you should discover this in anyone this allergy existing.
شما باید این حساسیت را در هر کسی که آن را دارد، کشف کنید.
You should say: “Sorry, we have nothing to do with you”.
باید بگویید: متأسفم، ما با شما هیچ کاری نداریم.
So that is for the people who have to have the privilege of this worship.
پس این برای کسانی است که باید امتیاز این ستایش را داشته باشند.
Today is specially a great privilege
امروز به خصوص این امتیاز عظیمی است
because it was not so planned,
چون آنقدر هم برایش برنامه‌ریزی نشده بود،
but it worked out, just worked out.
ولی نتیجه داد، واقعا نتیجه داد.
Yesterday we did lots of cleansing. Now, today tell your mind to rest for a while.
دیروز ما پاکسازی‌های زیادی کردیم. حالا امروز به مغزتان بگویید مدتی استراحت کند،
Tell your thoughts to stop for a while, and receive, receive more of it.
به افکارتان بگویید یک مدت متوقف شوند، و جذب کنید، بیشترِ آن را جذب کنید.
Everybody has benefited by this reception but you have to receive more.
همه از این جذب سود برده‌اند، ولی شما باید بیشتر جذب کنید.
There’s a capacity within you to receive.
درون شما ظرفیتی برای جذب وجود دارد.
Puja, as I have told you many-a-times, is not for My benefit, by any chance,
پوجا همانطور که به دفعات به شما گفته‌ام، برای من سودی ندارد، به هیچ وجه.
take it from Me. I’m much better off without it.
باورتان نمی‌شود. بدون آن من خیلی راحت‌ترم.
Because when the enthusiastic deities start emitting vibrations
زیرا وقتی دیتی‌های مشتاق با درخواست شما شروع به
with your asking - because you are saints, you see, just they are over-enthusiastic.
پخش ارتعاشات می‌کنند؛ چون شما قدیس هستید، می‌دانید. آنها بیش از حد مشتاق هستند.
And they are sitting there, busy-bodies, you know,
و آنها آنجا نشسته‌اند، به هر کاری کار دارند، می‌دانید،
they are sitting quietly waiting for a chance, you see, to emit vibrations,
آنها ساکت نشسته‌اند، منتظر فرصت هستند، می‌دانید، ارتعاشات را پخش کنند، تا شما را نجات دهند،
to save you, you see they want to just rush.
می‌دانید، آنها می‌خواهند فورا بشتابند.
They emit so much that they lose – “Just wait, just wait”.
آنقدر ارتعاش می‌دهند که باید به آنها بگویم: صبر کنید، صبر کنید.
They want to save you, they want to give you, they’re so anxious,
آنها می‌خواهند شما را نجات دهند، آنها می‌خواهند به شما عطا کنند.
in their anxiety you see - I like it, to see the way they are anxious.
آنها مشتاق اشتیاق داشتن هستند، می‌دانید، من این را دوست دارم که ببینم چطور اشتیاق نشان می‌دهند.
But you don’t suck it, and I have a problem there.
اما شما آن را جذب نمی‌کنید و من با این مشکل دارم.
Once they have given they don’t want to take it back.
وقتی عطا کنند، نمی‌خواهند آن را پس بگیرند.
You don’t suck it, so it has to go to the atmosphere, it has to disappear somewhere.
اگر شما آن را جذب نکنید، باید به هوا برود، باید یک جایی از بین برود.
Is directed towards you and you don’t take it; so where does it go?
اگر به سمت شما فرستاده شده و آن را نگیرید؛ پس کجا برود؟
It hangs into My tissues, it pains Me.
به بدن من می‌چسبد، باعث درد کشیدن من می‌شود.
So, sucking should be more. Sucking should be more.
پس جذب کردن باید بیشتر شود. جذب کردن باید بیشتر شود.
And just before the Puja you should say: “Mother, make me such
و درست قبل از پوجا باید بگویید: مادر، لطفا مرا چنان کن که از خداوند بیشتر جذب کنم.
Just pray that, with sincerity from your heart, just say that.
فقط دعایتان همین باشد، با خلوص قلب، فقط این را بگویید.
There’s another beautiful gesture I have seen, in Uzbekistan, it’s very good.
یک روش زیبای دیگری هم در ازبکستان دیده‌ام، خیلی خوب است.
They put both the hands on their heart like this, and just press it,
آنها هر دو دست را روی قلبشان این‌طوری می‌گذارند، به این شکل؛ و کمی آن را فشار می‌دهند
bending their head, asking. See, it creates a vacuum.
و با سری خمیده، دعا می‌کنند. می‌دانید، این باعث می‌شود ازخود بی‌خود شوند
That’s how they bow.
این گونه تعظیم می‌کنند.
It’s beautiful!
زیباست.
That’s very nice today.
امروز خیلی زیباست.